Suraj Suresh

346-467-5967 | surajsuresh27@gmail.com | www.linkedin.com/in/surajsuresh94 | Katy, TX

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Skilled IT professional with 3+ years of experience in Android App development using JAVA and Kotlin, automation testing and UI/UX design. Aspiring data scientist, proficient in Python and BI tools, looking to obtain a challenging position in an organization where I can use my technical and analytical skills and improve upon them.

EDUCATIONAL QUALIFICATION

MS in Information Systems, Data Analytics/ Data Science Specialization	December 2023
University of Texas at Arlington, Arlington, TX	GPA: 3.8
Master of Computer Applications (Computer Science Specialization)	May 2018
PES Institute of Technology, Bangalore, India	GPA: 3.6
Bachelor of Computer Applications (Computer Science Specialization)	June 2015
New Horizon College, Bangalore, India	GPA: 3.7

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: Java, Python, Kotlin, Dart, C, C++ **Web Technologies:** HTML5, CSS3, PHP, JavaScript

Version Control: Git **Database:** MySQL, SQLite

Tools: BI: Tableau, Alteryx, SAP S4Hana, | UI/UX: Adobe Photoshop | Game Design: Blender, Unity3d engine | Cloud: AWS |

Certifications: Tableau Certified Data Analyst, Google Cybersecurity Professional

WORK EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant- Digital Archivist

Sept 2022-Dec 2023

University of Texas at Arlington - Libraries, Arlington, TX

- Working on BitCurator to test, error-check and make digital preservation copies of legacy born digital media.
- Automated encoding of finding aids into XMLs and metadata files to upload on TARO, Preservica and UTA Libraries
 Digital Gallery by developing multiple Python Scripts.
- Preserved web pages by performing regular crawls and Quality Assurance on crawl reports on Archive-It.
- Implemented and presided over the implementation of **Archive Space** for the UTA Digital Archives and Special Collections.

Data Engineer Sept 2019 – Dec 2021

100Pi Labs, Bangalore, India

- Analyzed data from various platforms like Firebase, Google Play Console, Facebook analytics and developed actionable insights to improve user acquisition and retention.
- Gathered data from various analytics platforms and compiling reports and dashboards using Tableau to provide detailed overview of app metrics, usage metrics. Used Tableau stories to convey information in an easy to consume manner.
- Monitored performance of events and identified areas of interest within the apps, tracked user activity and gathered data in compliance with GDPR to prioritize fixes and integration of newer features in-app.
- Analyzed Data on Google Play Console, Facebook Analytics and Google Firebase to monitor KPI and using keyword analytics
 to drive more downloads. Contributed to the increase in DAU and downloads from 10 million in 2018 to 53 million in 2020.
 Used predictive analytics to predict user trends and potential usage growth using historical data.
- Implemented SEO and ASO strategies by performing keyword analytics from tools like App Annie, Sensor Tower to identify key trends in keyword usage and drove app downloads.

Senior Software Developer/Engineer

Sept 2019 - Dec 2021

100Pi Labs, Bangalore, India

- Developed Android applications using JAVA. Worked on multiple code refactors, switching from JAVA to Kotlin on some activities.
- Trained a team of junior engineers on the Selenium/Espresso framework for Android automation testing.
- Lead the development and deployment of features of multiple top rated Android applications with over 65 million downloads such as Pi Music Player, Pi Video Player.
- Worked on the integration YouTube features onto the app using licensed YouTube APIs and parsing JSON files using JAVA to display global content based on region.
- Designed and deployed app store assets using Adobe Photoshop and handled SEO and ASO of these apps using experiment data pipelines.
- Handled VC using git and git commands to actively work on multiple branches, code reviews, merges and commits.

Software Developer/Engineer

July 2018 - Sept 2019

100Pi Labs, Bangalore, India

- Developed fixes for customer issues logged onto GitLab
- Developed a user manual website using HTML5 and CSS3.
- Added events and event loggers into code to monitor user behavior, activities, and receive data on usage statistics.
- Running version-based deployment experiments on Google Play Console to A/B test different features based on region, Android version etc.
- Worked on the migration of the main code repository from BitBucket (Atlassian) to GitLab.
- Quality Assurance and Testing of newer app version and fixes before deployment.

ACADEMIC/WORK PROJECTS

The Game I've Played Dashboard

(Tableau)

Created a dataset and a <u>Tableau dashboard</u> as a pet project by applying visualization concepts, data cleaning, data gathering to display a story about the video games I have played, spread across platforms, regions, years and by developers. The project involved usage of basic to complex Tableau concepts of storytelling using data and creating strong visualizations to convey the information.

Pi Music Player / Pi Video Player / Pi Video Downloader

(JAVA/Kotlin/SQLite/Firebase Analytics/JSON)

A set of personal projects which later became popular and highest rated Android media applications with over **50 million+** downloads worldwide. As part of the core development team, performed and monitored programming and development, Quality Assurance, App-store optimization, KPI monitoring and analysis using Google Play Console and Firebase Analytics, UI/UX, YouTube integration using JSON scripts.

Automatic Detection and Classification of Growth Phases of a Bacterial Cell Duration

(MATLAB)

Used MATLAB to report on a rapid method for reagent less identification and discrimination of single celled bacteria using edge detection and basic morphology. Developed and automated a system that could analyze digital images of a bacteria and classify the bacterial growth phases by identifying geometric features of the bacterial cell.

Human Resource Management System

(ASP.NET using C#, MySQL server)

Developed front-end of a HRMS web application using C# on ASP.NET and back-end using MySQL server. Worked on implementation and addition of incremental updates and features such as including Google APIs for geo clock-in clock out, auto payroll etc. Worked on two separate modules of Employee and Admin

Title: Online Vehicle Showroom

(PHP,HTML, AJAX, JavaScript, MySQL)

Developed a virtual showroom web application using multiple web technologies like PHP, HTML and AJAX for widget UI's and JavaScript, SQL for handling store databases and functionality. Worked on WYSIWYG web builder to develop custom UI templates and wireframes prior to development of final build.